cool this is the
retina so yeah today in the written our
discussion we're discussing a video
where john spoke to unfortunately
i'm gonna have to call him some guy
because i don't remember his name
but uh they were talking about a variety
of metaphysical concerns
around like head
as always if anyone else has got a
thought
you go fast
his name is matt seagal uh
veloskin
so feel free to come forward with
whatever i think you should go for first
shut up
just for the first one to break the ice
yeah
all right so
the main takeaway
i had was that
it's sort of well i've got like a
hodgepodge here it's sort of
i'm realizing it's a bit disconnected
um but the main one was
the allusion to the whole cartesian
split
of mind and matter so a bit
especially because pretty sure
viveki goes over that in
awakening from the meaning crisis and it
made a lot of
it i remember it making a lot of sense
with respect to why we're in the meaning
crisis
i don't actually want specifics
so
i i think we should probably make a
project out of
making that clear although it seems
after talking to strowin he's done
a fair bit himself already
um
yeah anyone got any thoughts on that
well i mean that is basically my
wheelhouse as far as i can understand it
um but just based on what my natural
curiosity and interest in the subject is
so
i think that's a fair comment um
somebody else said they had one like one
line what was that
i have it and i i can't explain it to
you but i can tell you
the line the virtue of
reverence to the magnetic pull between
emergence and reverence
so in the third mine i was thinking
about the third mine with uh greg
jordan and john when they had discussed
the third mine
and um that is kind of where it came to
this
one after i listened to that and then
this i got the virtue of reverence
to the magnetic pull between emergence
and
reverence the pole between emergence and
reference
could you illuminate how that's a pole
a pull um
okay so they use they use the infinity
sign
go ahead i was just going to say it
sounds like you're using um when you say
magnetic pole you're talking about
opposites like north and south right
i think what can saying is that that the
emergence and emanation those make
sensible
opposites but emergence and reverence
that seem to be in opposition
okay so they used uh
in the uh video there was the infinity
sign
and on one side was the
uh
imminent emanation and the other side
was the emergence
so that when matt talked about it he
showed a picture
of the infinity sign and those are the
two um things and so
that's where i got the uh magnetic pull
from because when i think of the
uh the infinity sign that's what i think
about
where's the reverence though the is the
bridge between
emergence and emanation yeah
so they talked about virtues and what
was virtuous
right that's what i got from the video
so yeah okay yeah
okay
i have to be fairly brief today
but i think i can throw in on top of
what uh
lin just uh provided
not probably as original as you lynn but
just from my notes
and this ties back to last week's
conversation
generated by veloskin can you guys hear
me okay
yeah okay um
so john did one of his things where he
kind of logically ties
one thing to another to another to
another and
comes up with some outcome and my notes
have it
that he starts with rationality and
my recollection is that he's talking
about the circumscription
of rationality and the redefinition of
it
in other words may be harkening back to
what you said at the start about
cartesianism velocity etc
john in the video described it as
rationality is aspirational
so that kind of almost biological
frame that he puts on things and here's
the
kicker he said that must be tied to the
cultivation
of the virtue of reverence
and they started talking about the
metaphysics of reverence and the only
note that i really
stood out to me was that it must include
the theological
which in a sense brings us to where we
are
talking about religion that's not a
religion
so go ahead
i have a question for you in that regard
because what do you mean by theological
i mean um it seems to me that many
people have different ideas of what the
subject means and because everybody has
different ideas when we say when we
invoke the word
we don't actually have a common
understanding of what is meant and
that's actually one of the perhaps
problems with
the retina project is that we're all
coming at this from different angles so
um what do you think of is meant by
theology
yes that's a great question
so let's do the word thing um
uh theological someone's gonna have to
correct me maybe man well can you do
your etymology but isn't it theos is god
logical is like the study of etc
and uh let me run with this for just a
minute vlog um
stuart sorry so
inherent in the definition of theology
what does it mean to
me inherent in that is the very fact
that everybody has a kind of different
take on
god and i'm just going to use the word
god i'm sorry
i know that it's a um
both controversial and vexed
and frankly an exhausted term
um i think that's also intrinsic as you
rightly point out strong
to this project so in simple terms
theology means different people's
thinking about god
okay um i just want to add to that
slightly because
um i do i've also looked up the
etymology of theology and the
interesting thing
actually maybe vlaska told me but the
interesting thing was that the
root of theo is maker
so it's not just when we talk about
theology we're not just
talking about divinity talking
specifically
at least from a historical context when
um
people decided to name god theo they
were actually
they were looking for the creative
principle of the universe itself it was
very interesting to me because
the whole conversation regarding white
haters is recapitulation of creativity
but actually the very notion of
creativity is right there in
the concept of theology i think
personally it's why we have
you know all of our religious stories
are creation stories that's because we
worshipping
creation not just because we have this
idea that there was an origin somewhere
but because we are we've been worshiping
the idea of the creative potential
within ourselves
because that is how we have identified
fertility as opposed to
um well barrenness and and drought and
and
uh what have you you know um and so that
i mean that's been going on for
thousands of years
and with respect to reverence um
yeah i don't know i i i get the sense
that what's missing here actually is a
a understanding of what the whole is
like
science has given us a very clear
picture of the particularities but
we're at a total loss when it comes to
the whole um and i don't
i don't really have an argument for that
at this point but i mean that's just how
i feel
that's a great um refinement thank you
i love it
what can i say something
good because
for sure science seems a big part in the
in the verveiki's world view and uh i
guess
probably in the what what no would be
so is there any reverence out of that
worldview though
and how could we if the if there's none
how can we
maybe create some or or find
or why you know what i mean so
you're sort of pointing out that the
scientific world view doesn't have much
reverence in it
well no no no i'm not i'm just asking i
mean because i'm
of course they're all because it's such
it goes so deep
but maybe i would say yes
yeah that is sort of lacking in
reverence to a certain degree
i mean on the surface i would say
i think that's a complicated issue
actually i don't think that we should
try and look at it in a simplistic way
because
on the one hand yes i mean you know
science doesn't have any kind of sense
of meaning there all of these numbers
and formulas and whatever and
you know math is described as a certain
amount of energy but we don't actually
know what that energy is
it's more description of heart behaves
so you've got that on the one hand but
on the other hand you do have the
scientists
and they sit there and you do get
scientists with a genuine sense of
wonder about the world
yeah and that is well i think would work
for vacuum i don't think it goes far
enough to be honest but i think what
viveke would be
arguing in favor of is the idea of this
kind of scientific wonder about what the
world is like
being part of a ritual practice in a
religious setting more or less
did you say scientific wonder strewn did
i hear that correctly
uh well what i meant was like you know
um
somebody who
acts like stephen hawking you know
writing books about how you know what
what possibly happened before the big
bang it's all speculative there's no
clear answer but he's but he was you
know clearly curious about it he had a
sense of wonder about it like it filled
him
it he he kept wanting to grow himself to
the point where he could actually
uh grapple with these questions and i
think that that's the that's the the
general
emotional kind of complex of of feelings
or whatever that vivace is trying to
to to unearth and bring in to a ritual
context
and and maybe that's the point that
religions are missing
that kind of scientific wonder that you
can bring about and
compared to the world
well it could depend i mean i suppose
you could definitely say that of the
fundamentalists
yeah yeah
could you sort of see fundamentally yeah
i guess you could you could see
fundamentalism is like a
scientising of christianity
uh yeah sort of it depends i mean um
maybe not a modernized definition of
science but certainly an ancient one
you know because science well the root
of the word science is
the latin for cientia to see and so it
was
you know science was an attempt to see
into the world fundamentally
and so but it was understood as a
rational project right and
fundamentalism is all about making
trying to make religion like a rational
kind of
you know logical kind of a system almost
and then adhering to that logical system
as if adhering to that logical system is
what's going to bring you salvation
so you have your you have your doctrines
your beliefs your creed or whatever and
then you adhere to it and then you try
and behave
in accordance to what you hold and
that's fundamentalism in a nutshell
um so does anybody else have any of the
notes
here
okay so i do have a couple of notes
myself um
i don't know if it will be really
discussion topics it's
as such but i thought it was very
interesting for example that um
it was mentioned that kant favored an
imminent teleology in self-organizing
systems um and that this this kind of
view of
of biological systems is coming back to
the fall because
a non-tediological explanation seems to
be unsatisfying or a mechanistic
explanation of life is unsatisfactory
and incomplete
you may want to slow that one down a
little bit uh they're big ideas mr ron
you're
referring to can't okay yeah well i
don't i'm not terribly familiar with
content uh sorry solid
or sold solid uh your microphone
is picking up a lot of static there i
don't know if you can do something about
it
uh just perhaps if you're not talking
mute yourself um so
yeah great um yeah well i'm not terribly
familiar with kant on this particular
point i'm more
familiar with his distinction of not
being having knowledge of the thing in
itself
so i can't really speak with any kind of
expertise on this
but viveki did speak about kant and his
idea of self-organizing systems um in
his written eye lectures at least
um yeah so i don't know
would it help to go over those ideas or
are you familiar with them
not explicitly i'm a bit more like you i
know kant is a beast
and you don't want to you can get it
yeah okay so
world of [ __ ] unless you're careful
yeah um so i don't think it would be
very
uh productive to go into rabbit down a
rabbit hole about can't at this point
the the the bottom line is basically
that you have
um and with respect to whitehead at
least
or the project that he's chasing after
the problem was with the mechanistic
science of the
enlightenment era right there's no room
for anything acting on purpose so
everything is inert
the idea of teleology is this purposeful
action the problem is that we can't make
sense of the
um the causal loops of of living systems
without some without appealing to some
kind of intentionality or teleology
the the purely mechanistic description
of life fails to actually describe the
phenomena that we experience
and so therefore it's a short like um
what this is telling us is that it's
telling us that something about the
mechanistic view of the universe is
wrong
but we aren't exactly sure what it is
that that's what i take it to me
now we're like that to rip now right so
written or in sense you know that that
that's exactly it it's trying to come up
with okay so um people are in a meeting
crisis they've
well i would say john disagrees i think
but i would say
in large part that is because of the
loss of sense of purpose
and the fact that we have a worldview
that does not speak about purposes
is part of the reason why people you
know when they when they
when they live through that worldview
then they start to feel like everything
is purposeless
and i think that i think those two
things are related because i think if
you can't see your own purpose in life
then you are going to become
disconnected and disoriented and be
unable to make sense of your own action
in the world
if you are a thorough going materialist
and you believe everything is inert
yeah well that's what the worldview says
so if you if you
if you operate according to the
scientific worldview those assumptions
are in the language that you are using
so i mean there's like it shouldn't be
surprising that it will bleed through
not even necessarily at a conscious
level but simply at a subconscious level
where your
where your experiences eventually become
filtered through that language
yes absolutely
it's sort of this weird thing where
obviously a few people know this it is
literally a case of
you've set up your methodology in
advance
to basically push at push the purpose
out
then you've lived your whole life
according to that methodology and then
you've wondered why you feel like
there's no purpose
yeah that's basically what's happened
and the the thing is that
um with respect to the cartesian dualism
which i
they didn't really touch on too deeply
in this video but um
it's it it gives everybody
uh the grammar itself causes everybody
to cut the purpose out of everything
because you've got the the the mind and
materialism and the purpose can only
be articulated from a subjective
standpoint so to speak
i don't know maybe that's just stating
the obvious
but now it's it's it's speaking to
the sort of philosophical part of what
we may need to do with retinal which is
like as i've noticed oh yeah of course
but um
so i've noticed that uh there's this
sense we've got in
um
i've just noticed a lot of people sort
of are like compulsively objectifying
so it's as if they cannot accept their
experience just as it is
they get it so it's like they don't want
to live in a world where they're
just experiencing things they always
have to interpret it into something
objective
so it's like love is chemicals or some
crap um
so the sort of philosophical
part of retina may be sort of
addressing that problem i suppose
i think that in large part with the
appeal to the participatory kind of
knowing is
supposed to achieve just undermine that
kind of
emphasis on objectivity which i think
you know i mean science
is this kind of infecting science at the
moment and in a bad way
um but i don't really know what you can
do about that
yeah i would say and i'm going to have
to excuse myself
after this i'm really sorry but what
you're touching on
vis-a-vis participatory is correct
in in john's framework because he's
going to make a distinction between the
real
and the actual which
may be going to what veloskin said as
well about love
which is probably incredibly central to
all of this project
if i was to be really honest um
if you start making a distinction
between what's real
versus what's actual and maybe in a
simple term
if we said the actual is how descartes
boiled it down whereas the real is what
ritner is driving at and maybe something
like love
is real what falls out of that
i guess it comes down to what you mean
by real there
which is a yeah difficult question
oh yeah i'm gonna have to get back to my
note
on that yeah i'm sorry i don't have
time to justify what i said other than
it's something that is a distinction
that he makes clearly and i have not
justified it well enough i'm sorry
no problem um yeah it's not something
you need to apologize
for necessarily but i think it would be
useful to you to get an
you know for you to get an idea of what
you think is meant by reality
especially if because i mean i think the
thing is that he argues that um
that the notion of
reality has become so synonymous with
actuality so when you think like
if you accept that premise as a naive
western speaker who hasn't actually
investigated the topic
it's very likely that your idea of
reality would then be
what actuality is right and then if you
investigate that then you'll be able to
have a better idea as to what the
distinctions are and where you feel you
particularly want to go because maybe
you actually just want to follow in that
footsteps in that regard you know who
knows
um anyway
yeah absolutely i think it'd be unfair
to kind of hit and run
on this so let me look it up i'll give
you my note on it
and then i'll oh we'll have to go i'm
sorry
but i'll meet until then
don't worry he's done important
uh i do think
go ahead strong oh yeah i was just going
to say this this ties into
uh what was said in in the conversation
with respect to having to
reinvent rationality and reality at the
same time
and so yeah i was just going to open the
door to exploring that topic but i just
um could i did you have something else
that you wanted to say
yeah before we moved on to the the
potentiality part i thought
uh the talk of uh of
nietzsche in that regard was was really
interesting where he thought there was
not a lack of meaning
too much meaning and no way to
differentiate them
and then john brought up the nishitani
is
allowing for emptiness or potential
as like a trans trans-perspectival space
that
gives a shared ground in space from
which all the perspectives and meanings
can be
properly properly evaluated and what i
think you said alicia
raro argued that actuality and
potentiality need to be given
equal reverence which they're currently
not still in the west
um and then finally the connection to
the western notion of god
uh like aristotle's as complete
actuality
um which in a sense means it's like
static
and uh passive uh innocence which i
think caused
a lot of the problems whereas whitehead
is pointing to i think a useful shift
toward viewing god as part of an
evolutionary process
like the argena's circular
or the infinity model sort of sort of
thing
well i have a question for you in that
regard because um
whenever i hear talk like this it's like
there's there's always something lacking
like i'm not hearing the thing that that
that this to be the
the target of reverence and i understand
that there needs to be a recapitulation
but i was wondering do you have any kind
of specific direction you'd like to take
that into
because well as i say there's i feel
there's a lack in general
for an object of reverence within uh
theology well i mean evolving god
yeah like okay so i mean we've got all
of us this idea so god needs to be
changed you know like
we can't have the the static
intelligibility we have to go for the
dynamic intelligibility et cetera et
cetera et cetera it's like
okay i accept all of that but what does
it actually look like in terms of
of day-to-day practice or you know
what it actually um boils down to in
terms of the doctrines that we
that we would accept for our
institutions and so on and so forth you
know
like i just i don't see those details
and i don't see how one would would get
to those details from
what has been said so far
right well i suppose they would
imagine a more organic
like reciprocally participatory view of
the sacred
but they could still use symbols in
order to understand it like for
whitehead
uh creativity is the ultimate principle
like
his god which uh he defines as
the purpose is to create value in the
world and
the teleology is toward uh beauty
and i suppose that's like somewhat
subjective but not entirely
so you could use some shared symbols for
that i would think
okay yeah that's actually one of the
other things that
um it likes the fact that i was speaking
about the the roots of the word
theo meaning maker it was curious to me
that
that white had supposedly thought that
god was a creature it was a creature of
creation
like how can how can the maker be a
creature of making
that doesn't it seems to be like
circular almost
i didn't quite figure out how he did
that
seems strange to me but anyway um yeah
i'm not an expert i still need to read
more of my head but
before the video i was reading a bit and
he was
i think defining like he has a kind of
he doesn't have a dualism in the strict
static sense but he has a kind of thing
that reminds me of your your one and
zero sort of thing where he talks about
the objective
feelings and content and then the
subjective feelings and content
um the latter being value and that
god is constantly present within the
actualization
of each
occurrence as a kind of
constraint on the subjective uh
feeling or the value of every event at
all times
which can be like apprehended to varying
degrees
um but as far as like uh
called the creation out of nothing no i
don't think you would
describe god as that sort of creator
yeah fair enough guys um
and and ladies um gonna have to excuse
myself i'm gonna give you my best
uh effort at actual versus real
uh and then go um
so i think when john talks about actual
versus real he's trying to split apart
what we find mathematically measurable
like galileo and descartes
primary substance
but when john talks about real
he's talking about the transjective
uh in other words um i was just
looking at his evolve move play
lecture which is really good
and when he goes ahead and talks about
uh participatory knowing
he's talking about graspability as the
quality
of something that's real but is that
objective
is it actual not necessarily
but it's real
so i'm gonna in a very ginger kind of
way saying that my current take on what
he means by real
is something which can be
in between subjective and objective as
transjective
and it is what he calls a real relation
or real relationship
so there's some sort of reality formed
in the coupling
i know that's not totally satisfactory
but it's the best i've got for now
and i'm sorry i'm obliged to have to go
so really good talking to you all i'll
see you again soon
catch you later bye
yeah actually that that's good bringing
in the transjective i think because
uh whitehead i think has an analogous
concept where he
defines the like the presentational
immediacy or the objective feeling or
objective content
um as basically what hume
boiled down to when he went for radical
empiricism and then
the causal efficacy
of things was ignored by hume and
that's more where value lies but then to
bind those two together
uh can you can you
what do you mean by causal efficacy
basically just
uh like the chain of of causes in
general which
hume kind of got rid of with his radical
empiricism
okay which would also imply like be a
necessary
condition for any kind of purpose as
well i would think
um but to tie those two together
um kind of the subjective and objective
worlds to some degree
um you need some kind of symbolic
reference
which in some sense i think could be
argued to be kind of
related to the imagination but also i
think you could tie it to the
transjective as well
that's whitehead's symbolic reference
well yeah i don't know i just uh well i
have some
some qualms about how transactivity is
you being used as the bridge between
object and subjective but
in principle i don't have i mean i think
that that's
well that kind of approaches in the
right ballpark at the very least
yeah they didn't go over this so we can
go back to parts of the video
if you guys have things i have a few
things to it
no well yeah if you've got stuff to add
by all means but i mean i don't i don't
necessarily think that we should just
kill this discussion
right here but yeah so
also it's also worth talking about even
if it is a bit of a deviation
but yeah anyway
yeah you're just reminding me of your uh
the fourth thing that's not transjective
but
probably don't need to get into that um
well well just what is it very briefly
um i'm trying to remember what you
called it
oh you mean mine oh yeah so i had the
projective so it's the transjected
project of the opposite each other
um i was interested in
uh verveicky i think for the first time
saying that he thought of
metaphysically that intelligibility
is the metaphysical equivalent to
relevance realization which i hadn't
heard
i think he said the opposite i think he
said that intelligibility is like the
opposite pole of relevance
well as i heard him say he didn't want
to invoke a chorus like a correspondent
in a correspondence
theory truth kind of way but and so i
took it like it was a more of a
metaphorical correspondence
but the idea was that insofar as the
the universe itself is supposed to be
have the principle of intelligibility
relevance realization is to
intelligibility
as yeah i don't know this there's like a
but that that's more or less what they
have in common so like relevant
realization
i guess is life's attempted
intelligibility
yeah isn't relevance realization the way
that our sense data is
made intelligible isn't intelligibility
the outcome
well in part but the point is that from
a metaphor like
what he says in um with respect to
parmenides and everybody else who
followed in his footsteps is that they
um intelligibility was assumed to be the
ground of existence
and so everything the the question then
was okay
how how do we go about explaining the
intelligibility of the world
so from a from a philosophical game
perspective the
the game that they were trying to like
play was to figure out the world by
by trying to explain intelligibility
like
if the world is intelligible and you can
explain why the world is intelligible
then
i suppose it stands to reason that you
could explain a whole lot about the
world itself
and so the strategy will try to explain
the world by explaining its
intelligibility
whereas relevance realization fills in
that role of being the start
incidentally by just
stepping back from intelligibility
saying you start an absurdity
and then you realize relevance and then
you've created intelligibility and then
you go from that
and so you don't need to explain why the
world is intelligible but
by why the world is realizable relevance
is realizable
um i i think vivek would push back on
that particular
way of looking at things and i think
that's precisely because he doesn't he
doesn't want
the e rejects what he calls the um the
romantic and the empiricist
um opposition so um it's not that the
the world is neither a blank canvas upon
which we paint ourselves and the mind
isn't a blank slate that is just
um you know that is written upon by
society whatever
after we're bought um he rejects both of
those and so
what you're talking about sounds to me a
little bit you know
i don't know if you mean it this way but
the way that you described it to me it
sounded
um like the intelligibility isn't out
there in the world the intelligibility
is something that you add to the world
and i think the vacuum would push it
back against that but
i mean maybe i have the wrong read i
don't know
yeah no i was i was saying that like we
don't
start like we we don't have access to
the intelligibility
straight away i i but like
um uh no no
sure that's something that we have to to
make sort of i mean i i
that that's yeah i i would agree with
you that relevance realization is meant
to be the process that makes the
intelligibility in that sense
yeah but constrained by reality um
of course well yeah that just begs the
question what do you mean
by reality again yeah
well yeah okay so if we're defining
reality as
this subjective thing constrained by an
objective world
then i should say relevance realization
is constrained by
the objective or constrained by the
actual and
uh and creates reality but
um yeah i just misspelled in
putting reality though
well i i wouldn't say you misspoke
necessarily it's just that it's unclear
you know like like yeah yeah but you
know
this is going off topic a little bit but
also you know um the
conversations that john's having with um
greg enriquez
about um you know de-equivocating the
language
that's an ongoing project and i mean you
know as they do it you know i think
it's good for us to try and do the same
because if we don't yeah
you know we'd have subpar outcomes so
yeah exactly i mean the point that was
being made explicitly a moment
ago was our culture equivocates reality
and actuality
and so when i try to say actuality and
the word reality comes out that's
that's that's habits that have been
ingrained that yeah we're trying to
address so thank you
okay yeah fair enough but i mean you
know it could also be that actually you
think while reality
and actuality are synonymous you know we
should we should allow for that as well
in terms of of making sure that the
equivocation space goes away
yeah sure uh yeah sure does anybody else
have notes
um i had a point oh well
this might not be notes but another
follow-on on the subject of um
what's like what do we actually
worship um
in terms of uh
i can't remember whose point it was
where you asked
how they might fill in the gap
of like great but what does that
actually look like
does anyone remember
the gap of what um
i think it was maybe you today or
someone
was making a point uh
and then strong came in and said that
does sound good that does sound like
it's in the right direction
um but it raises the question of
like what what actually is it that we
that we worship or revere in all of this
but i can't remember what the point was
being commented on i just remember like
you know what i'd say next so if no one
remembers i can just say
but yeah it was the idea of god as
evolving
along with uh creatures it's like
yeah right they agree with is necessary
like
it kind of ties to another note i made
where they were talking near the end
about
how uh the solution is we
need to imagine ourselves as being
involved in the
in the enactment of god or the divine i
was participating
in it uh because again i think
uh aristotle's older idea of god is
totally actualized
and passive eventually um led to a loss
of purpose once people kind of figured
out most of the
apparent laws of nature um like there
was not much more
need for god um which i think was a
major component of the meaning crisis
and then how they talked about ancient
peoples felt the need to participate in
rituals on a regular basis or the world
would end so it was participatory
in that sense um and then that idea of
enacting god also reminds me of
alexander bard's idea of cynthiaism
creating god
in the digital age and he's also getting
pretty hardcore in the whitehead
regional
interesting yeah that's awesome
so the point that i was going to make is
just um
in the awakening from the meaning crisis
lecture series
there's this discussion of sacredness
and and the sacred
i don't i don't remember what the sacred
is but
as distinguished from sacredness but
sacredness was described as this thing
that invokes
awe and pushes you to the edges of
horror
to fill the purpose of horror but also
protect you from it
and he said he he made he claimed this
important necessary and of sufficient
feature of sacredness is
inexhaustibility um so in terms of
where you would look for a
a god to revere a god to worship um
or something sacred to worship i i think
it would be something
well the the claim that was made was
that it's
inexhaustible i kind of contemplated
three things
that have always been signifi have
over time become more and more
significant to me because of their
inexhaustibility
those three things are um like the the
infinite detail of the world
that we we can function in terms of
these categories and obstructions but
um all of these categories and
obstructions that we're dealing with
you can look at this precise detail
that's always being
simulated which just from a like
software simulation perspective boggles
my mind
um the other is just the sheer scale
that you can like look out and the
volume of the world
is huge and the third thing that seems
inexhaustible
is the combinatoric potential for
emergence um and then those three things
kind of multiply together to be
well even more inexhaustible um
so but i don't think that that's an
exhaustive list of inexhaustible things
those are the three that stand out to me
and then these points of dynamical
systems
and participating in like just imagining
participating
in the details of the world
that's a kind of meditative suchness
practice
um participating in the vastness of the
world is a kind of contemplating
contemplative mourners practice and
participating in the
emergence um i don't know what that
would look like but it sounds really
beautiful
so um but i'm only making these
connections now
in terms of connecting sacredness and
inexhaustibility to something that you
actually participate in
so that might be interesting
yeah i think that's really good bringing
in inexhaustibility that you reminded me
of of that term
um so i'm guessing you'd say of those
three the infinite detail is the
moreness
uh or sorry the infinite details the
suchness the sheer scale is the
moreness and then the combination
potential for emergence
is uh i guess the third factor
um as far as is that right
yeah i guess sir uh i mean
the emergence is almost just pointing
out that like if you have suchness and
mourners at the same time
there's a lot going on um
yes you could you could even save them
as that conjunction
yeah and then what i think
sorry velocity and i just want to say i
think sacredness and the sacred
uh differentiation was i believe sacred
the sacred is like a symbol for
sacredness which may or may not
be idolatrous if i remember correctly
yeah so i would simply say that that uh
such
this is the sacred is suchness and
sacredness is moreness
yeah because the sacred is a particular
instantiation
that's meant to lead you to the
you know sacred nurse in general
you know particular sort of brings it
pretty quickly
makes you think of suchness
yeah yeah the whole like bridging the
two
someone said it was like emergence
emanation with two
wouldn't it emergency is suchness to
mourn us and
emanation is modest to suchness
yeah it's very interesting
they were saying that whitehead seemed
to be a neoplatonist but not
an emanationist similar to aregina
that a mixture of the two that john was
talking about with
jonathan pedro
extremely i
um so what was this about a mixture of
the two
that whitehead like aerogena had that
kind of
uh infinity symbol like the graph uh
massigal
showed up between emanation and
emergence as opposed to
neoplatonism which tended to be
emanationist if i recall
oh yeah and they're sort of in it's not
like one
is supreme over the other it's a
dialogic
kind of thing yeah
yeah actually that's the note i made
which was uh
if you take that as
if you take that dialogic relationship
as a the sacred
and if you think of the universe as
you know that the universe has coming
out of the sacred as in
the dialogic relationship between
suchness and moreness due to like
through emergence and
emanation then
you could sort of see
like the point of life
as to basically live the sacred
this is all maybe nonsense but
i'm just gonna throw it in anyway
well i think that was maybe the
historical just
like you know um the whole the whole
idea of worshiping the gods was to be
closer to whatever the
portfolio the god was in charge of right
so you worship the god of fertility so
that you can be more fertile um
but there was there was this whole um
emanation emergence thing and and not
being an emanationist
um well i don't know maybe this
will be a bit too um abstract but
the other like like viveki talked about
the three orders right the nomological
the
moral and the narrative orders the
nomological order so far as i understand
is the way that
it's like the the laws of the world
basically
like the the the you know like e equals
m c squared that's like a
a law of the world almost you know
that's the way that the world operates
into constant
um
the thing is that if if you reject near
neo-platonic
emanation right um the whole the whole
idea of the nomological order was that
there was this
this this uh hierarchy between what was
sacred and what was profane
and so you have like mata which as segal
said um
according to platinus whatever it
doesn't strictly speaking doesn't even
exist right
um and then the other that that's the
profane arc and then the other
on the other end of the hierarchy is is
the um
is the one or the the the contemplation
the
the form or i don't know what you really
want to call it but um
the whole the whole logical order in
terms of the hierarchy is actually
built upon the idea that the emanation
is superior to the emergence
if you if you undermine that the
question is what remains actually of the
nomological order and i was wondering if
anybody had any thoughts about that
because it seems to me
that if if you do that move well then
you flatten the entire hierarchy
because you can't you can't say that
emanation is to be privileged over
emergence anymore so
it doesn't actually stand to reason that
all of the the potential or
or material stuff or the that it is
actually
inferior to what is you know most
actualized almost
realized almost real
so from an emanationist account how
would
you uh account for like picking
greg henry case emergence points
if you went back to a time period before
like bringing organisms with brains for
example
well um
yeah i mean the historical as i
understand it the the historical
approach was basically finances
approaches like okay well the the
the um the emanation is superior to the
emergence the emanation makes the
emergence possible therefore the
emanation depends upon the emergence i
mean sorry
the emergence depends upon the emanation
therefore it is superior
so end of story so it's not that the the
emergence isn't there
that the emergence is some is in some
way treated as the the
impure or the inferior things we've
gotten rid of
you see yeah so if you if you if you if
you if you create the infinity sign
between two
between both sides well then um you know
the idea is that okay so that
you've got god and then you've got the
angels and then you've got humans then
you've got animals and then you've got
um the dead you know like inert mata
whatever you you know
at each point there's this like it's
less actual right at least in theory
um so it would seem that the nomological
order is completely undermined by
putting in that that infinity between
the emergence the emanation i was just
wondering if anybody else saw that or if
they've got a way around it perhaps
i don't know if i'm familiar enough with
platinus but imagine
you can still have the i mean the thing
are gina and whitehead are both talking
about
obviously allows for both um
to influence each other in that kind of
top-down and bottom-up way
but maybe the question of whether the
nomological
order is or rather the emanation is
like morally valued more is
like a question of subjective
interpretation
i don't know well i mean that's just
the point is that okay so you had this
idea of a great chain of being right
being according to the description of
this thing the emanation is superior
it's not about whether or not it's
subjective or not it's a point the point
is that the story
if the emanation is superior to the
emergence the story of the chain of
being makes sense
if you if you if you undermine the idea
that the emanation is superior to the
emergence
the entire the entire narrative of this
chain of being becomes nonsense
and so if in effect if you accept this
this
this um dialogue between the two poles
then
neither side is superior to the other
and this chain of being
articulation becomes nonsense and so the
entire
that entire schema that that made sense
of the world in
in a way that people could interact with
it goes away and so then the question is
how
what do you replace it with
i'm not sure whether it follows that
having a dialogic interaction implies
that one is
superior to the other in some sort of
like normative sense necessarily does it
no i'm saying the opposite i'm saying it
doesn't i'm saying
that it actually undermines that premise
but that premise is necessary to have
the idea of a great chain of being
yeah i think what both john and
whitehead would say is that
uh some of the more like static or
fundamentalist dogmas
failed to account for the bottom-up
shifting or like the
i don't dispute that i'm agreeing with
you there but i'm saying it creates a
problem because now you don't you can't
make sense of the numerological order
anymore so you need a replacement
and i don't see what that replacement is
at this point
i mean like if if you are going to have
if you're going to have the idea that
there are different degrees of realness
right
so that for example matter is less real
than ideas
then um you have to have an account of
the world that makes that
that has something superior to something
else and something that's inferior
if you don't have that then the that
entire hierarchy
it becomes nonsense and it's undermined
and so the question is
how do you have an idea of realness if
you don't have a hierarchy
well i mean for one you could say that
they each have different contexts in
which they're relevant like the ideal
versus the material
rather than like a vacuum hierarchy
necessarily
like the hylomorphism of aristotle like
the form plus the
material actual
right but then the point is like okay so
so um
viveki talks about reality and illusion
right you don't want to be
in the idea you don't want to have
illusion but if you get rid of illusion
entirely if everything is real
right so you got mata and you've got
form and and they're both equally real
then to to have mata instead of form or
to form instead of matter
there's no way to privilege either point
right and so the question of well when
are you deceiving yourself
or when are you in the realm of illusion
if everything's real like
the the entire grammar of looking at the
world this way stops to make sense it
falsifies itself
right yeah i would think that
i mean maybe if you bring in the
transjective again it would need to like
be a coherent
relationship between the form and the
matter rather than
uh we call it like the confused or
equivocation
thing which is one of the main causes of
self-deception
yeah okay so i mean but what would it
look like specifically
that it would um that it would
give a give a sensible replacement that
allows people to act in the world
like the normative order
i think we might be equivocating the
nomological in the normative order now
that i'm thinking about it actually
um could be seen as the proper
the proper fusion of the form and the
material
such that they like create beauty in the
way john defines it for example
yeah well i mean i i you can as a
yeah you can appeal to the normative
order but it doesn't really solve the
issue of the neurological order being
being annihilated
uh the story of the neurological order
is this in some sense um like
exemplified by the post-modern
post-structural critique of
any attempt to make sense of the world
where
you essentially deconstruct by
by saying well look there's still some
illusion here so you
you haven't completely materially
explained to the world yet
um where essentially the post
structuralists
are raising empirical reality to such a
high
pedestal that none of your
ideas none of your theories are
quote unquote real anymore like is is
that
uh analogous or exemplifying what you're
describing
uh no it's a bit of a different issue um
what you're talking about is taking
somebody's standards and showing how
they don't actually
satisfy those standards what i'm talking
about is a different set of standards
that completely render the previous set
of standards
nonsensical well i never
i never mentioned like holding post
structuralists
to their own standards i was just saying
these standards the post-structuralists
when the argument that you're talking
about the post-structuralist the hard
empiricism and all of that stuff
what they it's it's part of their
rhetorical strategy
they they undermine somebody's
standpoint by showing how the person
fails to actually
fulfill their own criteria that they set
out
and therefore it's invalid that that's
the post structuralist move because the
structure
they always undermine the structure
using the structure's own claims about
itself
yeah right i see
so it's like
if that's a separate issue could you
have done that to
um to the neoplatonic
emanation argument back in the day as
well
what would that look like
i suppose you could have done it back in
the day i don't know if how many people
would have believed it or thought it was
thought you were even talking sense in
the first place but i mean
yeah i mean you know like if if you want
to really look at that kind of stuff
look at the
the cynics um like diogenes
and so on and so forth they had pretty
similar kind of
way of going about things this is the
post-structuralist actually
but yesterday you wanted to say
something
uh yeah unless jarvis had another point
feel free to jump in
um so it seems like regarding emanation
and emergence there's kind of
four different combinations uh
we could look at it and i i think you're
critiquing one in particular so
first you could have pure emanation only
which i don't think that's really um
one of the options here that we're
considering seriously um
i'm actually not even sure what
theologians would have had that
uh emanation plus emergence but with a
hierarchy of realness where emanation
is seen as higher in the chain of being
but emergence is also real
uh third would be emanation and
emergence are equally real like that
infinity symbol and uh influence each
other equally
and then emergence only which i assume
is kind of uh hardcore
materialism so i'm assuming that you're
critiquing
the the third one where emanation and
emergence are seen as equally
real and valued and are arguing for the
second one where there is both real
emanation and real emergence but there's
still
um hierarchy of realness where emanation
is higher
uh no um to be clear
i do not consider myself a realist so um
i don't i don't try and have a hierarchy
of realness i don't
for me um i don't know this is gonna be
really confused terminology but
sorry sorry uh hierarchy of
realness is still a kind of an odd
concept to me unless you mean like
uh the uh amount of detail but go on
well i mean historically that was you
know the the entire christian actual age
world view was
was predicated upon this hierarchy you
know it's kind of hard to miss
if you start studying it seriously so um
yeah okay so speaking personally i don't
consider myself a realist and that's
going to be really really
hard to unpack um let's say that i think
mata is real
um but but mind is ideal and so
it's the arc like the substance form
axis is between what is real what is
ideal
um and then of course you've also got
what is actual and what is potential and
that's
black so i don't i don't privilege
um what is real over what is ideal what
is ideal
over what is real they each have their
own domains um and so in that sense i've
i completely flatten out the the
the nomological order
but yeah as i say from from my
perspective i think that makes sense
because i'm i don't try
and try and have realness as my norm
um so yeah but the issue
like the thing you see the thing is okay
so i i don't consider myself a realist
but i see a lot of people saying
oh well you know realism realness yada
yada and the question is okay so what
does that actually mean
because the old formulation made sense
but this new formulation
is is challenging the old formulation i
can no longer make sense of
of your claims of realness anymore that
that there's a disconnect
and so i would actually say well maybe
you guys should join my side of the
fence and abandon
realism because that's that's the most
sensible thing to do
and and i mean fair enough like like i i
would say that that whitehead actually
has a point with regards to the infinity
symbol and
the the the feedback and the um crap i i
learned a new
word uh inamek um that means
uh when two sides are foes with each
other but they're not exactly
contradictions like life and death
it's like you can't have death without
life you can't have
life without death they but nevertheless
they kind of
are at each other's throats um and i
think
well the the the i wouldn't really use
the the
the hostility um idea i think that that
but i think there's the there is a there
is a similar kind of uh
um one begets the other kind of a thing
going on between emanation and emergence
so i actually like that part of of
whitehead and and viveki's thinking
um and and i and i i wanted to encourage
it i just think that that has
consequences for realism and for the
homological order which
in terms of britain are these
consequences need to be considered
yeah i agree but would you not say that
emanation could be construed
as the idealism half
perhaps i i i i need to think about it
because the question is
like okay um
well then in terms of actuality and
potentiality where's the emergence in
the emanation is it only something that
is
on the on between what is real and what
is ideal or
um is there emanation in emergence also
in the actuality potentiality arc like
and that that's actually something that
i haven't been able to figure out for
myself yet
so but but but i take your point like
like at least
at least with respect to to to
historical thinking there's a very
strong trend
to associate emanation with the general
and emergence with the particular
and that would follow you know with the
with the material and formal
um distinctions like you know between
um aristotle's moderate realism and
and um plato as well full-blown platonic
realism
uh it's a bit of an anachronism to call
it that but um you know those are the
distinctions
i think that you you're very much
following in the same kind of tradition
and i think there's there's some
validity behind that
like like i i can feel myself wanting to
make the same kind of moves
but as i said i've just got a bit of
qualms and i'm trying to still
figure it out right so you wouldn't say
potential is um if not isomorphic not
even
mapping to your definition of ideal
and actual as no no no no no no no um
yeah i know it's this is i i
i'm trying to actually explicitly for
example
split possibility and potentiality i
would say possibility is
what is ideal and then potentiality is
not it's not
like it's different and so um you see
this is exactly like
um people want to make the distinction
they want to they want to talk about
actuality and potentiality as if that's
the whole story like they don't need to
talk about any like what is real and
what is ideal
and then the actuality and the
potentiality together is taken
as what is real that that's very much
the
approach that i see people trying to
take out maybe that's wrong
my perception i mean um but we're yeah
so what i'm trying to do
is to um matter is real
mind or space is ideal and then energy
is actual and time is potential
and so the the possibility as such would
be it's more eternal so like space
rather than the potentiality of time
sorry i hope that wasn't confusing
i know you just reminded me of those
four yeah um
all right let me know velocity and if
this is getting too far off track but i
was curious
if you mean put possibility is uh would
you say that's like infinite and
potentiality is more
like getting close to actuality because
i kind of see those as a spectrum where
possibility
um is like in theory possible and then
potential is
you're getting closer to a particular
line of of a timeline where something is
able to be active um yeah i don't know
that that's kind of
hard for me to fit like
yeah i think if i try and respond to the
way you framed your question i'll be
misrepresenting my own position um
so i yeah i know i know that a lot of
people they they tend to see like
um potentiality as a refinement of
possibility
um i'm i'm not trying to think of it in
that way i'm trying to
think of it um well possibility is that
it's static and potentiality is dynamic
basically
and so the real and ideal are
polar opposites that together make up
the act like
well i would say the axis of
intelligibility i don't really have a
good word for the dynamic access yet but
let's say
let's call it a carpe or perhaps
relevance um
the other that that bridge is between
actuality and potentiality
and so you have to understand the four
together in order to to actually
be able to to to figure out my world
view basically
i don't know was that
yeah so you see it's like the um there's
a
the way that i look at it almost is like
space is like the false existence a
matter is a true existence in that
um space is the absence that allows the
presence
is the possibility for for the for the
the reality right
it's like it's only it's only because of
the the the the non-existence that space
has that the the existence of mata can
actually fill that space
and so there's there's a there's a or
they are opposites but in the opposition
you can actually make sense of them it's
like without the opposition it would all
be
you wouldn't be able to make sense of it
and i think that there's the same kind
of a dichotomy going on between energy
and time
and so there's the the the the
thing that you see now is the actuality
but the
the thing that that that you can't see
because it's not
actual is the potentiality which which
stress
stretches across time which isn't it's
inactive in some sense but you've got to
yeah i don't know it's hard for me to
find the words here but it did
yeah so i mean i'm trying to
to make it explicit exactly what the um
what the idea of potentiality would be
as divorced from
anything that is static in in the in the
sense of possibility of what is ideal
because i think i think that way of
talking is actually just that it's more
effective it allows people to think
to to function better but i mean that's
just a guess on my part
so you would say possibility has been
static since
the beginning of time like it's an
eternal set of
possibilities
um i would say that's the right way to
look at it i don't know if it is
actually that way i think that there's
um well this actually gets back to one
of the um things in the
one of the notes that i had um uh that
heidegger's project is extending
phenomenal
phenomenology into ontology like um
the question is how do we as living
individuals actually interface with the
world
like it's it isn't just that this
happens
automatically or that it is simple like
there
there are these complex structures that
that we have been built
out of that make this that make our
way of looking at the world possible and
i think
so yeah i i would i wouldn't necessarily
say that the same possibilities have
eternally been there
but i do think that there's something
about the way that we think that that
compels us to look at it that way and
that's the and
if you want to actually engage the world
in a healthy manner then you have to
accept that that's something
that that that's just the bias that
you're going to have to live with
basically
so yeah i don't know does it answer your
question
uh yeah and provides a new point well
yeah sorry to bring in the heidegger
stuff um so i think
heidegger was trying to when when
um john says that he was trying to put
phenomenology into ontology
um i think that's the same move that i'm
trying to make here with the trying to
push the first person into the third
person so that did i demand that
any attempt to to account for the third
person actually is also an account of
the first person account of the third
person
and i'm sorry that sounds particular but
yeah say that last part again
the i think the idea like if you're
trying to push phenomenology into your
ontology right
then you're trying to account you're
trying to give an account of the third
person
point of view that is also an account of
the first person account
of the third person point of view in
other words you're taking responsibility
for your own limitations in
what you look at and that is explicitly
part of what you
describe in when you describe what
you're looking at
yeah so i think um yeah i was gonna say
i've got one other note but i think
like it's actually weird how many things
we just
covered without me making to bring it up
yeah so um
i'm all out almost
any other
yeah i have a couple minor ones too but
if anyone else has it
um well actually there is one other
thing um i just noted the
failure of a non-creative ontology is
for godelian reasons
um i'm kind of speculating because i
don't i don't really
i'm not familiar with what john's
talking about well i mean i'm familiar
with good laws and completeness theorems
but i'm
specifically um familiar with the
historical background of who discovered
this and whatever
but what i think is going on there is
well godel's in completeness theorems
was basically the attempt to unify all
of the mathematical propositions that
exist
into a complete system the problem was
that every single time to create the
system
what you ended up with was a statement
this statement is false
and that self that self the fact that
that self-refuting
statement was possible within the
language undermined the validity of the
entire language
so i i guess what they're talking about
with with respect to a
creative ontology is that um
it would allow for something to be false
at one time and not false at another
so that this it wouldn't like you you
wouldn't you wouldn't
the changing nature of the system would
mean that you couldn't ever
nail anything down with finality and so
that there would always be
um relative islands of of meaningfulness
um
but i wonder like yeah i don't know this
kind of gets in
into the whole um numerological order
thing because
it seems to me that what goethe's
conclusion is that you can't describe
truth in terms of falseness and you
can't describe truthness and
truth in terms of sorry falseness in
terms of truth and truth in terms of
falseness
so those two the very attempt to have
an intelligible world would would force
you to to divide the world into
into a true and a false world like i
think
i think in some sense trying to build
your ontology out of intelligibility
is precisely what causes creates the
actual h2 towards grammar
and the the thing that we are confronted
with now
is that the scientific revolution has
actually undermined the very idea that
that we could
orient ourselves towards intelligibility
and live a
fruitful life
i don't know maybe that's a little bit
too out there
maybe clarify that last part because
how does science undermine our ability
to orient towards intelligibility
well because science is okay at least
in terms of the scientific world view
the scientific revolution that is
like in large part created by descartes
then you've got the the dualism right
and then there's no
meaning or purpose and the matter and
the scientific worldview only looks at
the matter and stuff and so
um that the point is like you made made
a similar argument with respect to is an
ought
there's no way to get to an ought from
an is at least logically
there's this gap and so what science
tells you is what is but it doesn't say
anything about what ought to be
and the fact that we the fact of the
matter is that if you hold
intelligibility as your ought
then you are left with this well then
then
all you end up with this is but there's
no ordinance in there is
because every single time you try and
look at the is you find there's no ought
and so um you're effectively isolated
from your own oughts
and it is this lack that that science
um because everybody says be objective
look at the facts but the facts never
speak about the values
and the values have always been left out
and it's the it's the language of values
that we are lacking now
so i am very interested in formal logic
and i can speak to
girl a little um i think that
god's incompleteness theorem is actually
contained within the is
like it's a failure of the is on its own
terms
um which is if you set up a
like mechanical well if you set up some
symbolic grammar that describes
propositions
and that proposition that that grammar
is sophisticated enough to describe
arithmetic
um then it's possible to describe
unprovable statements which doesn't mean
that they're false
it just means that they're um
it means it's impossible to reduce your
standard of truth
to a deductive system
um well like
so this there's this chain of problems
says the the ought from an is problem
um then there's the uh
then even if you disregard the ord
there's the
um the is from deductive logic problem
and then even if you disregard that and
you stay completely within the deductive
realm
then you still have to face godels in
completeness where
um i don't know how to frame it as a
blah from a blur but essentially
um you can't you can't create
an ultimate deductive system and say
things are deductively true if they're
provable in this system
um without like
without coming two statements that
uh can neither be there are statements
that are neither deductively provable
or deductively refutable um
yes which which means there's a conflict
entirely within deductive reasoning
never mind the fact that there's a gap
from deductive to
inductive or that there's a gap from
inductive to
um normative so
um i don't know so i find a lot of the
time when people
appeal to godel they're appealing to
godel as a as a symbol as a metaphor
um which may be partly what's happening
here i don't know if that like
technical refinement of what goethe was
actually saying
like it might not undermine the symbolic
argument um
but i'm interested in whether it
undermines or
refines the technical argument you were
making
no well i think the thing is that the
the the point is that the attempt to
divide the world into a true world in
the false world
is what you get when you adhere to the
norm of intelligibility and as i was
saying
like well what what um was saying
is that parmenides and platinus and all
of these other people they tried to
build an ontology out of intelligibility
so in that sense intelligibility was
then in other words they made the is
they ought
like i'm not i'm not saying that they
tried to derive it i'm saying they
explicitly said is this our ought
yeah interesting
like so so you've got like the entire
rational
you know the history of philosophy and
the rationalization of the mind
can be seen as trying to make the is our
ought and
then goodl's incompleteness theorems is
like finally
the acknowledgement that this is going
to fail like it's absurd
yeah i like that um
but then you see so this this what well
from my perspective this has questions
because then um
if if holding to the norm of
intelligibility requires you to divide
the world into a true world in the false
world
and if the scientific world view shows
us that this this division of a true
world in a false world is actually
unsustainable then where does that leave
us
and leaves us like in the middle of
[ __ ] [ __ ] creek without a paddle
that's the meaning crisis basically
um i'm still i still feel like there are
gaps between like
what goethe's incompleteness serum talks
about
like uh being surrounded by academics
you see a lot of people who
have that desire to move
in the direction of like deductive
completeness
and like it seems like you can
uh like godo's incompleteness serum just
uses deduction to show you can't go all
the way but i
i feel like you don't want to go any of
the way and
um and i like i don't think godel's
incompleteness serum has stopped
mathematicians from
obsessing over deductive true versus
false reality they've just accepted that
um that they won't be able to finish the
project of true versus false
um but yeah
it's it's still it's still very
interesting that like goodwill's
incompleteness theorem is the only
threat to people
because they started equivocating
you know reality with their
intelligibility in the first place
and yeah that's very insightful
i don't think john would say that um
that there's a lack of of a false world
in the sense that
he sees like self-deception as both
uh false in terms of the is and
um negative in terms of an odd like it's
the lack of a transjective
uh participatory relationship to reality
so in that sense there's kind of still a
fusion of
of the is in the op whereas if someone
maybe you're trying to bring back but
where's john's false world there isn't
one so where what is the the meaning of
the illusion exactly you can't you can't
pin it down
it becomes unclear i think it would be
more of like a false
reality in the sense of having a false
relationship between the self and the
world
like a mismapping of uh coherence
right but so then um but okay so
so but this is the issue then right
because if if the scientific world view
is showing us that there's no inherent
tediology in things that there's no
purpose that you can't infer the purpose
then there's no prospect of a mismatch
because it is you that is generating
whatever
purpose you see and so where could
what could possibly what what could you
hold it against
to show a mismatch
uh i would think it would need to bring
back
like the the phenomenology of the
subject like their own transjective
apprehension of reality rather than you
know treating it as
the objective empiricist fallacy that he
talks about
right what what are they apprehending at
that point
when they're in self-deception
no yeah how do you determine the
self-deception
what are they what are they deceiving
themselves about if there's no
if if what they you know
so like where is the mismatch between
what and what
i would think between what is
i think you could bring the relevance
and relevance realization into this part
and you could
argue that relevance could be construed
as as the
odd part of the equation i think
yeah but okay so if it should be
relevant then the idea is that it's
relevant
to me right so it's once again as me
personally
if i find it relevant so for example
if i don't want to live anymore well
then all of the stuff that could kill me
it's no longer relevant like am i
deceiving myself because i don't want to
live anymore
the the idea of talking about this in
terms of truth and falseness falls away
and that's you see i'm saying if you no
longer have this division between true
and false
falseness then fundamentally realism
like
as a as a cultural cognitive grammar it
fails to satisfy
uh i don't know if i could speak to that
example very coherently but
i guess i mean i've heard uh yeah sorry
paul vander clay make the argument
against sam harris in the sense that
bringing things back to the the reality
of the
of the subject for norms um
makes it you know purely individualized
but that still
feels to take into the into account the
fact that
um given the shared uh
set of human biology and so on and the
way the mind works
there's generally going to be a large
degree of what is relevant that is
shared intrinsically um and then the
higher
or the more um
i forget if john has returned good
relevance really
i i don't dispute the fact that there
will be like you know
a consensus and that there will be
outliers and that people will be able to
you know get rid of the outliers because
well you're
you're not lying we don't want you in
that kind of thing i don't dispute it
the point is
that you can't tell their li the
outliers well you're suffering from
self-deception
like that that claim just doesn't make
sense anymore
yeah i'm trying to remember how john has
described like
good relevance realization from poor
uh which i guess you could say brings
back a separate
kind of value but i think you would
answer something like that which i would
agree with
like yeah i don't know i i i would say
yeah i suppose you could you would
probably say something about wisdom but
the thing
if we're talking about concrete
particulates here then i would say that
the
um how does he put it
making meaning is making meaning makers
because we are meaning makers
and so the idea is you see it's kind of
tautological that we ought to make
meaning
and that we make meaning by making
meaning makers and so it's a
once again that that's the that's the
kind of the the fertility and the making
kind of idea coming to the fore again as
far as i see it
um and i don't dispute that i think that
that that that's that's that's right
it's you know there's something
deeply accurate about it but but that's
not you don't articulate that in terms
of truth and falseness
well i i think we've gone over this
slightly before i think you could say
that
increasing the amount of meaning and
meaning makers which is the only
intrinsically relevant
thing also increases the total
amount of intelligibility being
transjectively
like not perceived but participated in
by more individuals
so in that sense maybe you could make
the total increase or the total amount
of intelligibility as
as the norm or the odd and then use that
definition of agape to to feed it back
on itself
yeah but the the problem is that when
you when you adhere to that norm of
intelligibility in a personal way
then you get up you hit the the goat
all's in completeness they're a problem
and then
the whole thing just falls apart because
the grammar doesn't make sense anymore
like that's my objection
um it seems like there's there's like
two reasons to disagree with someone
though
um and if the people you're criticizing
equivocate those these two things and
that's a fair criticism
but would you agree that um
like if if someone's
born with some innate desire
to uh end their life
for uh knowing they desire to preserve
their life
that um you can't claim that they're
deceiving themselves
when they act in a self-destructive way
um but at the same time
uh like in fact
it's it's possible that they're simply
definitively not
deceiving themselves they're actually
acting rationally
um but
at the same time it is possible for
someone to
not be innately self-destructive and
still [ __ ] themselves
into self-destruction right
um yeah i mean i don't see why that
wouldn't be possible
i think we just need to break down that
the concept of the self
and like for example plato's monster
lion and the man
um to problematize people claiming that
they know they want to harm themselves
yeah that's interesting um and i guess
in some sense there's some part of them
that does want that outcome
and they're just like resolving the
conflict between internal parts of them
by
submitting to some self-destructive part
um
but i mean that's kind of beside the
point which is just that um
that um
i i guess i'm trying to refine strengths
well my understanding of strength
criticism that
like it's not that it's not that
self-deception doesn't exist
um it's that you can't
you can't summon like you can't reduce
all disagreement
to one person is wrong and the other
person is right
um and in that sense
right like
well yes and um the the the meaning
crisis and the historical development
has
actually been you can see it in our
history it's like people have been
trying to behave according to that that
that norm and it's failed and we are
here today
in the rubble of the failure trying to
like figure out well
what what's next if that's how i see it
yeah that makes sense to me
so if someone harmed them if they were
just under the influence of like a
shallow module
harm themselves uh couldn't you argue
that they're decreasing their
capacity for meaning and intelligibility
and therefore
it's they ought not to
or if they're getting um
well i mean yeah but the i i mean
i don't really see how that solves the
issue
i mean like i i could argue well you
ought to worship god so you know
jump into the sun
you know what's the difference
because if you're making is if you're
like taking uh making
is your ought all the way through like
in a more comprehensive sense
of intelligibility rather than like
the empiricism or romanticism then
you could argue that someone who's
harming themselves or others or becoming
addicted
is decreasing their capacity for meaning
and meaning making an intelligibility
and therefore
they ought not to but you you're just
upping it in the stack at that point
you're not resolving anything
you're saying well okay so the sr
distinction is one level up
yeah i just i don't see what that would
you can obviously say it but i don't see
what it would accomplish
it's not gonna i mean if they disagree
it's not a i don't think that if you say
to everybody well live according to this
way of life and if if you see that they
aren't they're decreasing their own
intelligibility well then they
they're harming themselves or whatever i
mean yeah you you could say that but i
don't think ultimately that it works i
think that ultimately if everybody tries
to live that way
they discover things that that
completely derails their
their faith in the system as a whole
living according to uh the art of
increasing meaning
uh if you're making the author if you
well no that that's something else isn't
it that's not making
is your ought in terms of
intelligibility
increasing the amount of intelligibility
like increasing right
so are you are you are you drawing uh uh
um are you saying that that meaning and
intelligibility are one and the same
thing
well i mean there could be meaning that
is intelligible to others but not you
but like
people can't really access it without it
being intelligible to them right so it
wouldn't really be relevant
so it's like you need both yeah but hang
on hang on
saying that that intelligibility is a
necessary part of meaning isn't the same
thing as saying that intelligibility is
meaning
right so i don't know like i don't want
to make that claim
personally maybe you do i don't know
some people i think do but i don't like
that so
um i wouldn't well yeah and that's
that's my whole discomfort because i
think the people that do make that move
then they use
um intelligibility as an excuse to
create a hierarchy and then they start
bashing other people over the head with
that hierarchy and um
well ultimately it just doesn't work
does it it can't live up to its own
standards
to to borrow about you know from what
the what i've learned
from the post-structuralist yes so when
john talks about
susan wolf's idea of the making
meaning and meaning makers as the only
thing that's intrinsically relevant
you think i think uh he is primarily
talking about what you're defining as
meaning or intelligibility there
with his definition of agape kind of no
i think that's yeah that's something
that
that's that's speaking to something that
is beyond intelligibility
and i mean i don't mean unintelligible i
just mean it's not
um not expressly aimed at
intelligibility
it's meta-intelligible
yeah i mean i think there's kind of like
a gradient between
just pure intelligibility like as
somewhat irrelevant fact and then deep
meaning
but they're all necessarily
intelligible in order to be like
perceived by well i i i could say that
um
intelligibility is necessary but it's
not sufficient
and that that's yeah i mean not that in
a deep sense that that gets to what my
grievance with respect to
to realism is
yeah so if you added in meaning or an
opt
how do you connect it other than other
than intelligibility being
necessary but not sufficient how does
that resolve the gap
between the is and the ah even if you do
bring back well then the
then the the the is is necessary and the
auth is sufficient
so that's the it is the gap it's like
it's basically partitioning the two and
then you've got a
you then the question is well what is
the relationship between necessity and
sufficiency
and that well i mean that is the
question whereas i'm concerned maybe
that's exactly the
you know the world is exactly the
relationship between necessity and
sufficiency
i don't know maybe that's entirely
unhelpful
well it still i guess brings the
question of where you're getting where
you're getting the ought from
aside from like innate biology so
so well um
i mean i'm i'm no yeah okay so you're
looking at the innate biology and you're
saying
there's an is aha right
so what i would say in in response is
um for me that there is is dynamic i
mean sorry there is a static and that
does is dynamic and so if i'm getting an
auto i'm not getting it from the is i'm
getting it from the does
and so that's also i mean that's moving
away from the big bottom
all right did you say our last part
again
yeah so you've got like like you've got
being and becoming is and does
right so the noun and the verb
so i say the the the norm with respect
to acting it's going to come from the
verb not the noun
it's like i mean that's to me it's
almost self-evident
like obviously yeah
because you need the norms make sense of
the verbs not the nouns
and you see but the attempt was with
respect to this chain of being in this
in this um
and the nomological order and this um
and the realism the intelligibility
was to create well truth is the is the
good and falseness is the bad i'm saying
no there is truth in falseness but there
is also good and bad and these are kind
of orthogonal to each other
right yeah i thought it was also
interesting that
whitehead they were talking about
him thinking one of the most important
tasks of philosophy in the modern world
is to secularize the function of god i
don't know if you guys wanted to discuss
that also
that seems to me like uh well yeah i
don't know
it's acute terminology but i kind of
think that that's a
it's a contradiction in terms
but i don't know i mean what do you mean
by secular
i mean sort of like what both vervice
and
jordan peterson were trying to do like
it's not the end point
because it doesn't imply in and of
itself the reverence for the sacredness
that's
necessary for well for even just the
adaptational uh rationality john is
talking about but it can get people to
reflect upon why that is necessary in
the first place and then eventually get
to the point of worship or reverence
yeah i understood it as um
you you've got the function of god and
you're trying to
synthesize it with
well it says secular but you know i'm
thinking of like
maybe the individuality yeah the
scientific world for you basically
so because because at least at the
moment it seems to me it's just like
well they're non-overlapping magisteria
that just
like don't even touch
i i i would say that i like your
thinking but
i think at the end of the day based on
what you're trying to do this sounds to
me like you're trying to get the ought
from the ears again
i had i mean i
i i don't have a problem with what
peterson or viveki are doing obviously
um but i don't know just just the the
way of phrasing in terms of
secularization i think that that's a
that's a
bull's errand is the goal
just compatibility
well i suppose yeah i mean um
i think it's just a way to make it
vibrate yeah i really i
i i i yeah i certainly accept the idea
of a recapitulation of god
in in more modern terms or in in terms
that a modern person could understand it
and function you know and then like
enacts
the functionality of it
i don't yes about i just i probably just
nitpicking over the phrasing that's all
i think it's reasonable to point out the
phrasing might not be
optimal but i do feel like that was sort
of what was meant
recapitulating yeah i know sure
um i i don't dispute that for a second
there was one other minor point i had
the last one was just that
john i hadn't heard him mention before
that he wanted to add exactation
as the fifth e to 4u cognitive science
and with the brain circuit
reuse hypothesis um and how cognition is
like deeply analogous to evolution and
emerging from it
i don't know if you've talked about any
of that before but i heard it
ah he's mentioned it once or twice
it's not a big thing though well it
depends
i don't know i'm not entirely happy with
it but you know
i feel like it could be useful in
hashing out more specific things
because it will because that kind of
thing will sort of help
maybe with stuff like symbolism
or something yeah well actually yeah no
i i i
just wanted to bring that up um it
actually maybe there's
there's um there's a lot of potential in
it because
well that that exact of tendency would
really explain why um for example
um you have 80 agreement that um
uh what was it again the circle is good
and square is bad
or evil
but you know the exact nature of
cognition could it could
precisely be what what the cause of that
is
yeah yeah i think
it also might be important for
like uh specifying
different religious traditions
for what is viable for different people
depending on
um what like frameworks they've grown up
with especially
i don't know i haven't looked into it
but if the brain circuit reuse
hypothesis
is somewhat dependent on age like if
there's
much more synaptic pruning um during
like
adolescence or something and therefore
certain symbols
and frameworks for sacredness are going
to be more or less viable for people
which i think it's kind of an argument
for pluralism to some extent
do do we have a confirmation on whether
that's
true or that's just manifest
what's crosstalk well the adaptability
of the brain is there
has it been a physical
um yes it has at least if you can
well you can for example um people with
bad absolute epilepsy like there's a
i think it's before the age of seven um
people
well there's two age gaps i remember
really quick like there's the the
gap between zero and two years and then
two years and seven years
um and there's this ah crap i can't
remember exactly specifics but there's
like a difference between
exactly how severe the operation can be
and still have a person recover from it
after seven years of age it starts
getting very very dicey and the point is
that at that very young age the brain is
so plastic
that if you lose one hemisphere the
other hemisphere can actually grow
so that it takes over those operations
it's still young enough but if it
happens in your older age well
you're gonna suffer seriously if you if
you lose hemosphere
yeah that's not an argument
against f4
well it's proof that it happens right
sure but
exactly i already conceded that it
happens right like
i'm trying to figure out the reason that
it happens
right like could you because you could
just say right like when you have more
structure
changing structure is more difficult
right
and especially if you have like
dependencies upon dependencies upon
dependencies if you take
away fundamental dependencies you might
like collapse the whole system right so
that would be an argument
for reduction in adaptability but that
also it might be an argument for
not having certain dependencies right
like
black watch for example
well you have developmental stages
right so the developmental stages are
in my opinion the
having a sufficient way of relating
on one level so that you can build a
meta level on top of it
right so but by that using that metaphor
if you're getting rid of dependencies
you're effectively keeping people in a
childlike state
because you you're denying development
not necessarily but
like that is a different discussion
well then yeah i don't know i i guess
i'm not sure what you're talking about
maybe talking about the things then well
i'm i'm first talking about the
principle and then i'm
we can discuss the validity of
of having alternatives later like i
don't
think they need to be in the same
discussion
i mean i think you're saying that you'd
want to have enough resiliency
by not having too many like excess
connections
well the i would i mean in this context
i think the resiliency is the existence
of the excess connections
precisely but why after the pruning you
don't have the resiliency anymore
because you've lost the excess
actually yeah
so there would be a decrease in
adaptability
after adolescence right yeah it's
like from from my mind it's a it's a
trade-off it's like
yes you lose the the malleability but in
in exchange you gain the the the
the proficiency like you know expect
expertise has to you have to solidify
expertise at some point in order for it
to become expertise
yeah so it'd be an increase in
efficiency
perhaps yeah i don't yeah i suppose i i
i don't know i need to think like every
single time john uses those terms i
think he's using it the wrong way around
and like
my brain just flips around
look at that really carefully
just one quick um so do we have any more
notes on the video because we're almost
at two hours and it seems like it's a
fair time to finish the recording
yeah i'm tired of discussing the video
at this point i don't know if anybody
else has anything to add but
i think we can call it
i mean it wasn't from the video directly
but it was about
that last point we were making the
exhaustion
yeah well i'm happy to continue the
conversation i just i'm i'm talking
about whatever we're talking about now
it's like
um i've i've mined whatever it is out of
the video and i'm happy
okay well then we'll just put an end to
the recording
and thank you everybody for listening to
this discussion and i hope you'll tune
again
in the next week